Guide to the Anderson and Nostrand families papers and photographs ARC.199
Brooklyn Historical Society
Anderson and Nostrand families papers and photographs
1844-1914
Brooklyn Historical Society
Nostrand, Lewis Pease
Anderson family
ARC.199
0.67 Linear Feet in one glass plate negative box and one manuscript box.
This collection dates from 1844 to 1914 and documents three generations of the Nostrand and Anderson families through photographs, documents, and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lewis Nostrand Anderson, Jr., 1960 and 1965.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
Series 1: Photographs, circa 1880
Series 2: Lewis Pease Nostrand memoir, 1897
Series 3: Peter and Maria Anderson papers, 1844 to 1863
Series 4: Miscellaneous family papers, circa 1879 to 1914
Biographical note
Lewis Nostrand Anderson (1872-1939) was born in Brooklyn and lived in the Williamsburg neighborhood. He was the son of Samuel Cowdrey Anderson (1849-1908) and the grandson of Peter and Maria Anderson. Peter Anderson was born in New York City and Maria Anderson (nee Nelson) was from Williamsburg. They married on December 20, 1847, moved to Brooklyn circa 1850, and lived on Boerum Street between Broadway and Bushwick Avenue in Williamsburg. Lewis Nostrand Anderson was also the grandson of Lewis Pease Nostrand (1823-1900; born George Lewis Pease Nostrand), a businessman and resident of the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood.
Lewis Nostrand Anderson graduated from Columbia College (now Columbia University) with an M.D. in 1895. He married Laura Chapman and they had (at least) one child, Lewis Nostrand Anderson, Jr. (b. 1904), who also attended Columbia University and graduated in 1926. In 1928, Lewis Nostrand Anderson, Jr. then attended Columbia University School of Architecture and became a landscape architect. He began working for the City of New York in 1934, where he served for many years.
Other Finding Aids
Item level description and digital versions of images from the collection are available for searching via the image database in the library under the object ID prefix V1974.11. Please consult library staff for more information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
The Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Columbia University holds a related collection: Anderson family papers, 1828-1876 (MS#0033)
Scope and Contents
The Anderson and Nostrand families papers and photographs date from 1844 to 1914 and measure 0.5 linear feet. The collection documents three generations of the Nostrand and Anderson families and includes photographs, tax receipts, a marriage certificate, a wedding invitation, a menu from a caterer, a membership certificate, a diary, and a handwritten memoir.
Receipts (financial records); Boerum Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Tax records; Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Watkins Glen (N.Y.); Sea Cliff (N.Y.); Families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Memoirs; Family papers; Reminiscences; Taylor Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Tennis -- Pictorial works; Transcripts; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Commerce; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Architecture, Domestic -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Marriage certificates; Outdoor recreation; Exterior views; Photographs; Negatives (Photographs); Wedding announcements; Menus; Certificates; Street photography -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Dwellings -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Anderson, Peter; Anderson family; Anderson, Maria; Nostrand family; Nostrand, Lewis Pease; Fish, Daniel; Anderson, Lewis Nostrand
- Series 1: Photographs, circa 1880
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of two sets of material.
  The first is comprised of 47 items including 36 black-and-white glass plate negatives, 10 black-and-white photographic prints (reproduced from the glass plate negatives), and one postcard. The material documents the Anderson family and their family home that was located at 149 Taylor Street in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. Included are numerous photographs showing Lewis Nostrand Anderson, as well as informal group portraits. The home at 149 Taylor Street is well-documented and includes both front and back views of the house. Views of the Prospect Park lawn tennis courts, as well as images of Lewis Nostrand Anderson, his cousin Albert Wade, Helen Brown, and others in lawn tennis attire are also represented. These items also documents Anderson family holidays spent in Sea Cliff, Long Island, N.Y. and in Watkins Glen, N.Y. This set makes up the accession V1974.011.
  The second set is comprised of a wooden stereoviewer accompanied by 131 stereographic slides. These items belonged to the family. The slides depict nature views, sites and city views, the 1876 Centennial in Philadelphia and the art displayed there, comedic scenes, and three unidentified images that seems to be family portraits. This set makes up the accession M1985.299.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The stereoviewer in this series (M1985.299.1) is not currently available to researchers.
  - [Photographic prints reproduced from glass negatives], circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Glass plate negatives], circa 1880 (Box Glass Negatives 2, Item V1974.12.1 - V1974.12.35)
  - Stereographic slides, circa 1870s; M1985.299 (Box 1)
    One wooden stereoviewer (M1985.299.1) accompanied by 131 stereographic slides (M1985.299.2-132). The slides depict nature views (2-39), sites and city views (40-79), the 1876 Centennial in Philadelphia (80-99) and the art displayed there (100-114), comedic scenes (115-129), and three unidentified images that seem to be family portraits (130-132). This set makes up accession M1985.299.
    The nature views and sites and city views include Watkins Glen, NY; Lake George; the Delaware Gap; various locations in California, including Yosemite and Mammoth Trees; Niagara Falls; various locations in New Hampshire; upstate New York and the Hudson Valley; Mexico; Salt Lake City; locations along the transcontinental railroad; Washington, DC; Philadelphia; and Manhattan, including Central Park terrace.
- Series 2: Lewis Pease Nostrand papers, 1879-1897
  This series consists of a handwritten memoir of Lewis Pease Nostrand and his 1885 diary (calendar). The memoir was written in 1897 when he was 74 years old and provides reminiscences of his life including descriptions of Brooklyn before it was incorporated into New York City; his Brooklyn Heights neighborhood as experienced as a child; the loss of his father when he was seven years old; his church affiliations and attendance; and how he rose from errand boy to a partner in the cork importing business, Truslow & Nostrand. Nostrand's memoir also includes reminiscences of his marriage and family life including the day he purchased the family home located at 149 Taylor Street in Williamsburg. The memoir is dedicated to his three daughters Heattie, Millie, and Minnie.
  The series also includes a six-page partial transcription of the 69-page memoir and a wedding announcement addressed to Lewis P. Nostrand for the wedding of Rev. William H. Hoag and Millie A. Nostrand, 1879.
  - [Nostrand, Lewis P. (1823-1900) autobiography memoir], 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lewis Nostrand transcription, circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [L. P. Nostrand diary], 1885 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Wedding invitation], 1879 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Peter and Maria Anderson papers, 1844-1863
  This series consists of tax records, dating from 1844 to 1863, pertaining to real estate located on Boerum Street in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. The tax records name Peter Anderson, Maria Anderson, and Daniel Fish. The series also contains the marriage certificate of Peter and Maria Anderson, issued in 1855, though they were married on December 20, 1847.
  - [Marriage certificate], 1855 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Tax records], 1844-1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Lewis Anderson papers, circa 1900 to 1914
  This series contains a membership receipt to the Hanover Club in Brooklyn for Dr. Lewis N. Anderson, 1914; and a handwritten menu and cost estimate from Kiefer Caterer, located at 1074 Fulton Street in Brooklyn, to Dr. Lewis Anderson, undated.
  - [Invitations and correspondence], 1885; 1977.348 (Box 1, Folder 6)